<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle of the moste myghty [and] redouted Prince Henry the .viii. by the grace of God Kyng of England and of Fraunce, lorde of Irelande, defender of the faithe, and supreme heed of the churche of England, nexte vnder Christe, writen to the Emperours maiestie, to all Christen princes, and to all those that trewly and syncerely professe Christes religion</title>
            <title>Ad carolum Cesarem Augustum epistola. English</title>
            <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13081.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109412</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845060</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 44:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle of the moste myghty [and] redouted Prince Henry the .viii. by the grace of God Kyng of England and of Fraunce, lorde of Irelande, defender of the faithe, and supreme heed of the churche of England, nexte vnder Christe, writen to the Emperours maiestie, to all Christen princes, and to all those that trewly and syncerely professe Christes religion</title>
                  <title>Ad carolum Cesarem Augustum epistola. English</title>
                  <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Thomae Bertheleti Regii impressoris.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D. XXXVIII. [1538]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Henry VIII.  Ad Carolum Cesarem Augustum epistola.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Catchword, leaf A2r: neither.</note>
                  <note>Verso of tp reads: Hereunto also is annexed the protestation .. [i.e. part 2]. Copies of part 2, when present, are listed at STC 13090 et seq.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴ (B4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 13081 on film.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN EPISTLE OF THE MOSTE</hi> myghty &amp; redouted Prince Henry the .viii. by the grace of God Kyng of England and of Fraunce, lorde of Irelande, defender of the Faithe, and ſupreme heed of the churche of England, nexte vnder Chriſte, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Emperours maieſtie, to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten Princes, and to all thoſe that trewly and ſyncerely profeſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IN THIS EPISTLE BOTHE</hi> the cauſes are playnely declared, why the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hyghenes owght neyther to ſende nor go to the Councill indicted at Vincence, and alſo how perylouſe a thinge it is for all ſuche as profeſſe the trewe doctrine of Chriſt, to come thether.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HEREVNTO ALSO IS</hi> AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed the Proteſtation made the laſt yere by the Kynges hyghenes, his holle Counſayle and cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, as touchinge the Councille inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tted at Mantua &amp;c.</p>
            <p>¶Rede bothe o Chriſten Reader, truthe is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge home, longe afore beynge in captyuytye, ſteppe forth and meete her by the waye: yf thou ſee her preſence, embrace hir, and ſhewe thy ſelfe gladde of her retourne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>HENRY THE, VIII, BY THE</hi> grace of God kynge of Englande and of Fraunce &amp;c. ſaluteth the Emperour, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten princes, and all true Chriſten men, deſyringe peace and Concorde amonges them.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>VHERE</hi> as not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſithens a boke came forthe in our and all oure counſailes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, whyche bothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned many cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, why we refuſed the Councylle, than by the byſhoppe of Romes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped power fyrſte indycted atte Mantua, to be kepte the .xxiii. daye of May, after proroged to Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, noo place appoynted where it ſhulde be kepte. And where as the ſame boke dothe ſufficiently proue, that our cauſe coulde take no hurt,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:3"/> neyther with any thynge doone or decreed in ſuche a company of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte men to one ſecte, nor in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther councill callyd by his vſurped power, we thynke it nothynge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, ſo ofte to make newe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, as the byſhoppe of Rome and his courtes by ſubtiltie &amp; craft, do inuent ways to mock the worlde by newe pretenſed general council<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Yet not withſtandynge bicauſe that ſome thynges haue nowe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, eyther vpon occaſion giuen vs, by chaunge of the place, or els through other conſiderations, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nowe beynge knowen to the worlde, maye doo moche good, we thought we ſhulde do, but euen as that loue enforſeth vs, whiche we owe vnto Chriſtis faythe and rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to adde this epiſtell: And yet we proteſt, that we neither put forth
<pb facs="tcp:9936:3"/> that boke, neyther yet we wold this epiſtle to be ſet afore it, that therby we ſhulde ſeme leſſe to deſyre a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councille, thanne any other prince or potentate, but rather more deſirous of it, ſo it were free for all partes, and vniuerſal. And further we deſyre all good princis, potenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, and people, to eſteme and think that no prince wold more willyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be preſent at ſuche a council than we, ſuche a one, we meane, as we ſpeake of in our proteſtation, made concernynge the councill of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua. Truely as our forefathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented nothynge more holyer than generalle Councilles, vſed as they ought to be, ſo there is almoſte noo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing, that way do more hurt to the Chryſtian common welthe, to the faith, to our religion, than general councils, if they be abuſed to lukes,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:4"/> to gaynes, to the eſtablyſhement of errours. They be called generall, &amp; euen by theyr name do admonyſſhe vs, that all Chriſten men, which do diſcent in any opinion, may in them openly, frankly, and without feare of punyſhement or diſpleaſure, ſay their mynde. For ſeing ſuch thinges as are decreed in generall councils, touche egally all men that gyue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thervnto, it is mete that euery man, maye boldely ſaye there, that he thynketh. And verylye we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that it ought not to be callyd a generall councylle, where alonly thoſe men are harde, whiche are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned for euer, in all poyntes, to defende the popyſſhe parte, and to arme them ſelfe to fyght in the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Romes quarelle, though it were agaynſte god and his ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. It is no generall Councill,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:4"/> neyther it oughte to be callyd gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, where the ſame menne be onely aduocates &amp; aduerſaries, the ſame accuſed and iuges. No it is againſt the lawe of nature, eyther that we ſhulde condeſcende to ſo vnreſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a lawe agaynſte our ſelfes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we ſhulde ſuffre our ſelfes to be lefte without all defence, and beinge oppreſſed with greatteſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, to haue no refuge to ſuccour ourſelfes at. The biſhop of Rome and his, be our great enmies, as we and all the worlde maye welle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue by his doinges. He deſyreth nothynge more than our hurte, and the deſtruction of our realme: doo not we than violate the iudgement of nature, yf we gyue hym power and auctoritie to be our iudge? His pretended honour fyrſte gotten by ſuperſtition, after encreaſed by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:5"/> and other wayes, as euylle as that: his power ſette vppe by pretenſe of religion, in dede, bothe agaynſt religion, and alſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the worde of god: his prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, borne by the ignorancie of the worlde, nouryſhed by the ambition of byſhops of Rome, defended by places of Scripture, falſely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande. Theſe .iii. thynges we ſay, whiche are fallen with vs, and are like to fall in other realmes ſhortly, ſhall they not be eſtablyſhed agein, if he maye decyde our cauſe as hym lyſteth? If he maye at his pleaſure oppreſſe a cauſe mooſte rightuouſe, and ſet vp his, moſte againe truth? Certaynely he is very blynde, that ſeeth not, what ende we maye loke for of our controuerſies, if ſuch our ennemye maye gyue the ſentence. We deſyre, if it were in anye wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:9936:5"/> poſſible, a council, where ſome hope may be, that thoſe thynges, ſhal be reſtored, whiche nowe being depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, are lyke, if they be not amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to be the vtter ruine of chriſten religion. And as we do deſyre ſuche a councyll, and thynke it mete, that all men in all theyr prayers, ſhulde craue and deſyre it of god: euen ſoo we think it perteyneth vnto our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, to prouyde bothe that theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe ſubtilties hurte none of our ſubiectes, and alſo to admonyſhe other Chriſten princis, that the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome maye not by theyr conſent abuſe the auctoritie of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, eyther to the extinguyſhing of the true preaching of ſcripture (that nowe beginneth to ſpring, to grow, and ſpred abrode, either to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyng of princis liberties, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myniſhinge of kynges auctorities,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:6"/> and to the great blemyſſhe of theyr princely maieſtie. We dout nothing but a reder not parciall, wyll ſoone approue ſuche thinges, as we write in the treatiſe folowynge, not ſoo moche for oure excuſe, as that the worlde may perceyue bothe the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye deceytes, craftes, &amp; ſubtilties of the papiſtes, and alſo, how moch we deſyre, that controuerſies in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygion maye ones be taken awaye. All that we ſaid there of Mantua, maye here well be ſpoken of Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. They do almoſte agree in all poyntes. Neyther it is lyke, that there woll be any more at this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cille at Vincence, than were the laſt yere at Mantua. Trewelye he is worthy to be deceyued, that beynge twyſe mocked, woll not beware the thyrde tyme. If any this laſte yere made forthe towarde Mantua, and
<pb facs="tcp:9936:6"/> beinge halfe on theyr waye, thanne perceyued, that they hadde taken vppon them that iourney in vaine, we do not thynke them ſo foolyſhe, that they woll hereafter ryde farre oute of towne to be mocked. The tyme alſo, and the ſtate of thynges is ſuche, that matters of Religyon maye rather nowe be broughte far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in trouble, as other thynges are, than be commodiouſely intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and decyded. For where as in maner the hole worlde is after ſuch ſorte troublyd with warres, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combred with the greatte prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons that the Turke maketh, can there be any manne ſo agaynſte the ſetlynge of relygyon, that he wolle thynke this tyme mete for a general Councill? vndoubtedly it is mete that ſuch controuerſies, as we haue with the byſhoppe of Rome, be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:9936:7"/> as they are, that is much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than that they maye eyther be diſcuſſed in this ſoo troubleſome a tyme, or elles be commytted vnto proctours, without oure greate ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdie, all be it the tyme were neuer ſo quiete. What other prynces wyl do, we can not tell, but we wyl nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaue our realme at this tyme, neyther we wyl truſte any proctour with our cauſe, wherin the holle ſtay and welthe of our realme ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, but rather we wyll be atte the handlynge therof our ſelfe. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept both an other iudge be agreed vpon for thoſe matters, and alſo a place more commodiouſe be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for the debating of our cauſes, all be it all other thynges were as we wolde haue theym, yet maye we laufully refuſe to come or ſende any to this pretended Councyl. We wol
<pb facs="tcp:9936:7"/> in noo caſe make hym our arbyter, whiche not many yeres paſte, oure cauſe not hard, gaue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ageinſt vs. We woll that ſuche doctrine, as we, followyng the ſcripture, do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, ritely to be examinid, diſcuſſid, and to be brought to ſcripture, as to the onely touche ſtoone of true ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge. We wyll not ſuffre them to be abolyſſhed, ere euer they be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed, ne to be oppreſſid, before they be knowen: moche leſſe we wyl ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre them to be troden downe beinge ſo clerely trewe. No, as there is no iote in ſcripture, but we wolle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende it, thoughe it were with ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdie of oure lyfe, and perylle of this our Realme: ſoo is there noo thynge, that doth oppreſſe this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or obſcure it, but we woll be at continualle warre therwith. As we haue abrogated all olde popiſhe
<pb facs="tcp:9936:8"/> traditions in this our realme, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che eyther dyd helpe his tyrannye, or increaſe his pride: ſo if the grace of God forſake vs not, we will wel foreſee, that no newe naughty tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions be made with our conſente, to bynde vs or our realme. If men wyll not be wyllyngly blinde, they ſhall eaſily ſee euen by a due and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident profe in reſon, though grace dothe not yet by the worde of Chriſt enter into them, howe ſmall thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of the byſhop of Rome is, by the laufull denyall of the Duke of Mantua for the place. For yf the byſſhoppe of Rome dydde erneſtly intende to kepe a councyll at Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua, and hath power by the lawe of God, to calle princis to what place hym lyketh: why hathe he not alſo auctoritie, to choſe what place hym lyſteth? The Byſſhop choſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:8"/> the Duke kepte hym out of it. If Paule the byſhoppe of Romes auctoritie be ſo great, as he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, why coulde not he compel Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus, Duke of Mantua, that the Councylle myghte be kept there? The duke wolde not ſuffre it. No, he forbadde hym his towne. Howe chaunceth it, that here excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyons flye not not abroode? Why dothe he not punyſſhe this Duke? Why is his power, that was wonte to be more than fulle, here emptie? wonte to be more than all, here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge? Dothe he not call men in vayne to a Councylle, yf they that comme at his callynge, be excluded the place, to the whiche he callethe theym? Maye not Kynges iuſtely refuſe to come at his call, whan the Duke of Mantua may denye him the place, that he choſeth? If other
<pb facs="tcp:9936:9"/> prynces order hym as the Duke of Mantua hathe doone, what place ſhall be lefte hym, where he maye kepe his generall Councill? Again. If Prynces haue gyuen hym this auctoritie, to calle a Councille, is hit not neceſſarye, that they gyue hym alſo, all thoſe thynges, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute the whiche he canne not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe that his power? Shall he call men, and woll ye let hym fynde no place to calle them vnto? Truely he is not wonte to appoynte one of his owne Cyties, a place to keepe the council in. No, the good man is ſo faythefull and frendely towarde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſeldome he deſyreth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be his geſtis. And admitte he ſhulde calle vs to one of his cityes, ſhulde we ſafely walke within the walles of ſuch our enmies towne? were if mete for vs there to dyſcuſſe
<pb facs="tcp:9936:9"/> controuerſyes of Relygyon, or to kepe vs out of our ennemyes trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes? meete to ſtudye for the defence of ſuche doctrine as we profeſſe, or rather howe we myghte in ſuche a thronge of perylles be in ſauegarde of oure lyfe? Well, in this one acte the byſhoppe of Rome hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he hath none auctorytye vppon places in other mennes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynyons, and therfore yf he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe a Councille in any of thoſe, he promyſeth that that is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man to perfourme, and ſo may he deceyue vs agayne. Nowe if he calle vs to one of his owne townes, we be afrayde to be at ſuche an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes table. we ſaye, better to ryſe a hungred, then to goo thenſe with oure bellyes fulle. But they ſaye, the place is founde, we neede noo more ſeke where the Councill ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:9936:10"/> be kepte. As who ſaythe, that, that chaunced at Mantua, maye not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo chaunce at Vyncence. And as thoughe it were very lyke, that the Venecians, menne of ſuche wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhoulde not bothe foreſee, and feare alſo that, that the wyſe Duke of Mantua ſemed to feare. Certes, whanne we thynke vppon the ſtate, that the Venecians be in nowe, hit ſeemeth noo verye lykely thynge, that they woll eyther leaue Vincence, theyr Cytye, to ſo many nations, withoute ſome great gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of ſouldyers, or elles that they beinge elles where, ſo ſore charged allredy, wyll nowe noryſſhe an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye there. And if they wolde, dothe not Paulus hym ſelfe graunt, that it ſhulde be an euyll preſydent, and an euyll exaumple, to haue an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Councille? How ſo euer it ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:9936:10"/> be, we moſte hartely deſyre you, that ye woll voucheſafe, to rede thoſe thinges, that we wrote this laſt yere touchynge the Mantuan Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cille. For we nothynge doubte, but you, of youre equytye, wyll ſtande on our ſyde agaynſte theyr ſubtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and fraudes, and iudge (except we be deceyued) that we in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyneſſe, neyther gaue ſo moche to oure affectyons, neyther withoute greate and mooſte iuſte cauſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed theyr Councilles, theyr Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Decrees. Whyther theſe our wrytynges pleaſe all menne, or noo, we thynke, we oughte not to paſſe moche. No, if that, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differentely is wrytten of vs, may pleaſe indifferente reders, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyre is accomplyſſhed. The falſe and myſtakyng of thynges, by men parcyall, ſhall moue vs nothynge,
<pb facs="tcp:9936:11"/> orelles very lytell. If we haue ſaid aughte agaynſte the deceytes of the Byſſhop of Rome, that maye ſeme ſpoken to ſharpely, We praye you, impute it to the hatredde we bare vnto vyces, and not to any euyll wyll that we bare hym. Noo, that he, and all his, maye perceyue, that we are rather at ſtryfe with his vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than with hym, and his: oure prayer is, bothe that it maye pleaſe god, at the laſte to open their eyes, to make ſofte theyr harde hartes, and that they ones maye with vs (theyr owne glorye ſet aparte) ſtudy to ſet forth the euerlaſtynge glorye, of the euerlaſtynge God.</p>
            <p>¶ Thus myghtye Emperoure Fare ye moſte hartely well, and ye Chriſten Prynces, the pylors and ſtaye of Chriſtendome, Fare ye har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely well. Alſo all ye, what people ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9936:11"/> euer ye are, whiche doo deſyre, that the Goſpel and glory of Chriſt may floryſſhe, Fare ye hartely well.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶Gyuen at London oute of oure Palace at Weſtmynſter, <date>the eyghte of Apryll, the nyne and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye yere of oure reygne.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:12"/>
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS THOMAE BERTHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LETI REGH IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SORIS. EXCVS. ANNO. M.D.XXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9936:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
